thank you
so this is the avija suta suit on
ignorance um and go to the 1061.
because it is said that no first point
of ignorance is evident before which
there was no ignorance and afterwards
ignorance came to be
um so as you said quite a lot ignorance
is beginningless
you um ignorance of what
you can answer in many different ways
but uh the point is practically speaking
you don't start in a neutral position
you already start okay begin hindered
obstructed obsessed limited restricted
so that's what ignorance is
why do you why is it that um
I mean yeah obviously it's because
that's that's how it is but um
why is it so sort of difficult to
um
not see
the possibility of not ignoring well
because you have no reference point
that's not affected by ignorance
so any standpoint you take
but takes an ignorance it's rooted in
ignorance and that's why it's so difficult so no
and that's why it's so difficult so no
standpoint you can just suddenly show
your situation there are no markers for
it
any standpoint you take will be ignorant
so
top to bottom
so then what do you do how do you then
figure your way out well that's where
the gradual training comes in
you figure it out
by upholding certain
behaviors sense restraint
sense restraint
virtue which in return diminishes not
that you can see it not at a time you
can see it later on
after which your efforts would have been
verified but initially you can't see
you can make some sense you know out of
it if you're authentic and intelligent
and so on but fundamentally
comes down to doing it regardless of
your standpoints
keeping the precepts guarding the sense
doors watching your intentions and so on
in that diminishes
that wishes a weakens that vicious cycle
of of ignorance feeling more ignorant
standpoints feeding more standpoints
to those training precepts
and tame your mind within that
then you get to see your situation from
the inside
and that's all the party basically and
that's what we said in that the seven
the relay chariots
like the the views will be purified not
because you figured it all out
intellectually and made sense out of it
the views are purified when your
behavior is purified where the composure
is regained within that
so samadhi results
direct result from nothing else other
than sense restraint and precepts
purification of the views is a result of
that but that's not uh natural that's not
but that's not uh natural that's not
something that
um
one would
I mean yeah it's what is natural is to
is to want pleasure oh yeah
fundamentally the most natural thing is
to put your standpoints first yeah
the the craving for the views
that's where the views are the most
blame world I think the wrong view is
the most blameworthy thing is the Buddha
said um so yeah you would go against that
um so yeah you would go against that
grain against the tendency not that you
can stop having views but you can
certainly uh stop emphasizing them
so put your views aside review your
behavior your actions and purify it like
like a skilled Goldsmith would be
purifying gold first from coarse
impurities then more refined impurities
than more refined impurities
and then next thing you know you don't
have those standpoints anymore
you can see what proceeds to the
standpoints they're gone because they have been
they're gone because they have been
unplugged because you've seen the
context or you've been able to no
because you purified it
be purified into sense restraint
uh watchfulness of your intentions
General Taming of your mind
and then these views have lost
their their power their weight
the the the standpoints yeah the the
wrong emphasis he's disappeared
so you can have still thoughts and
standpoints but they won't be heading
the same weight they won't be emphasized
because now you know exactly
how the mind is stained how the views
are diminished
and how the freedom from suffering is is
developed
through gradual training not through the
opinions on it
and the opinions that persist would then
just be without that weight would be a
correct representation of what you did
so the Right View
so like you know how to kind of ignore
no no no because arohan's mind cannot be
Untamed anymore
cannot be provoked anymore cannot be
disturbed cannot be prepared thus no no
views no standpoints can arise
so The Suitor gives
10 fuels for the uh
for ignorance for ignorance um
so just to clarify before getting there
so ignorance is not on the level of the
views some it's not on the level of oh I
some it's not on the level of oh I
haven't read enough to figure things out
it's on the level of that self-induced
delusion distraction greed aversion
through your acts and your choices
that is what ignorance is choosing to
turn a blind eye that's basically what
The Suitor says yeah so
um
yet it is evident that there is a
specific condition for ignorance
I say that ignorance is fueled by the
five hindrances hmm um
um
as you say yeah it's it's acting out of
acting out of pressures obsessions I
mean the five hindrances
they will boil down to Greater version
distraction one way or the other
so choosing to act out of those things
you are fueling a vision you're fueling
the attitude of ignoring turning a blind
eye of not being clear
the translation of mohai's delusion
sounds like delusion
you're a fool kind of me but I like the
the translation of distraction because
yeah yeah practical thing you know when
you distracting yourself
there's some recognition there
but I guess so most
person who's ignorant is distracted
yeah and he's ignorant because he keeps
himself distracted yeah
but yeah he doesn't know that he
necessarily distracted him
yeah in the same sense and intoxicated
person he's not aware of his that he's
drunk I was until his SOB was up I was
just going to bring up the intoxication
like even the the way that the Buddha
talks about like the intoxication of
Youth the intoxication of life in health
in and health in the sense that like old
age sickness and death are not things
that are hidden from people things that
are they're very obvious nor are the
things they will come later they're
already here exactly
all around you can hmm full full sick
die get old and so you you could
pay more heeds to them but it's like
this yeah they feel it intoxicated
an intoxication cannot exist on its own
in the same sense you would sober up if
you stop drinking yeah so the fact that
you're not sobering up means because you
still consuming alcohol
in this sense the fact that you're not
sobering up from these intoxications is
because you're still consuming things
that keep you intoxicated
Central desire acting out of aversion
and distraction
and it's like a similar principle of
trying to basically forgetfulness almost trying
to basically forgetfulness almost trying
to deliberately induce forgetfulness of
the things that are obvious yeah because
it's like a coping coping habit and but
they only it's funny because you only
need to try and forget that thing if
it's already kind of
some on some level recognize that it's
that it's a problem otherwise you
wouldn't need to to
forgetfulness is a pleasure a safety
even though you know
what you what you're forgetting about
just that
in a shutting your eyes covering your
head is Pleasant
but if that's the funny thing that I
give you
like if if you are saying even in terms
of intoxication like if you're in a
a situation where you know it's really
you know you you must not forget you
must not become just careless or
something I don't know you're driving or
something or whatever most people at
least if you have some degree of
of carefulness or what was you or
whatever you wouldn't you wouldn't you
know if if you might uh I don't know
drink a small amount of alcohol or
something but if you were to realize oh
I'm actually I'm starting to become
intoxicated it would be
seen as dangerous it would be seen as
okay I can't let myself forget this
because I need because I can see the
danger of forgetting
so like
in other words you can only
you know take pleasure in forgetting if
you're already intoxic intoxicated to
some degree yeah and that's that's
exactly the point like uh
you already start as being intoxicated
so there's no reference point of
sobriety yeah the neutral position is
seeing the danger well that's how you
work towards the neutral position then
yes you could still technically become
careless but then the danger is much
more apparent in doing so as as opposed
to somebody who is in the beginning when
there's like no reference point for the
danger and also like that's why like you know I
and also like that's why like you know I
know when I when I started it in the
sutras you know back as a Layman and
so obviously you know you have all these
views and so on but I remember like you
read the students and you just seemed
almost as if a matter of a fact
that monks would just get the right view
upon going into seclusion oh that is too
Buddha then they go and dwell diligent
and withdrawn
but they're the same that was kind of
not quite fitting with the with the
assumption that the right view is on the
level of figuring out things and having
this this magical kind of breakthrough
Insight type into stuff that just
suddenly surprised you
so it was like why did they diligent
about what are they withdrawn from where are
what are they withdrawn from where are
you like oh so if somebody makes the
effort Right View was the necessary result of
Right View was the necessary result of
it if somebody makes that right effort
and then just he comes he talks with
Buddha the word instructs him he goes
and he dwells Resolute and diligent and
then in no time
and then another one and then another
one and then another one and then you
may think oh well because you know
they're lucky talking to the Buddha and
so on but no they were the ones diligent
in Resolute so diligent in Resolute
about what about spinning their mind
constantly around how to figure this out
how to figure this out wizard of
rehashing everything
well maybe some to some extent but there
is there's probably some more kind of
practical unifying thread that all these
different monks regardless to you know
some one might have arrived through
faith another might have a ride through
through discernment uh and reasoning
another one might have arrived through
composure either way they all simply
partake in diligence and resoluteness of
keeping the Mind away from unwholesome
States and they will arrive at the Right
View and out of hand ship
because you realize aha because that's
where the emphasis is it's not on a
magical breakthrough through
sensation experience of your meditation
it's not certainly through Scholastic
figuring out
you know
the implicit meaning the hidden meanings
of the Pali terms and it's also not on
the level of accounting or on account of
just made a reasoning you can reason all
you want
but as I said many times before
if the mind is not attained through the
gradual training in the right order or
withdrawal and diligence again diligence
not I'm diligent I'm going to walk 20
kilometers and carry
50 liters of water on my back and live
on top of a mountain and I'm diligent
I'm diligent sure that's one way of
being diligent but that's not the
diligence we talk about diligence that
matters is diligence of recognizing the
unwholesome intention whenever it arises
on a day-to-day basis and simply not
acting out of it and during it without
losing context in regard to it
every single time no exception
that's all that's literally the old that
you need to do
and then whether you reason whether you
Ponder whether you speculate that will
also fall into place
I say that the five hindrances are
fueled by the three kinds of misconduct
um so building's gone up my body's
speech of Mind acting out
um and the three kinds of misconduct I
feel by a lack of sense restraint which
is basically implicit with yeah yeah so
oh why can't I stop acting out
I'm sure everybody at some point has
asked themselves that question
well here's why
here's why
because you're not restrained not
strained enough
you're still willingly consciously
in full volition
choosing nonsense restraint when those options
nonsense restraint when those options
present themselves
sure maybe not as bad as you you used to
be or something but effectually if you
still can't help but act out is because
you still have not purified the
restraint
the relay chariots
seeing one's responsibility
yeah exactly seeing that the direct
reason for you still acting out is Dior
um Choice choices made on a day-to-day
basis that contradict the center
strength
so you're still fueling it
and then it burns
you can be so surprised all you want but
you are the one pouring the fuel
so I say the lack of sense restraint is
fueled by a lack of mindfulness and
situational awareness um so
like you're saying this this um this
contradiction yeah that you're acting
out of so you lose sense restraint
because you lost the context so how'd
you lose the context then how did you
lose mindfulness
but is that happen accidentally just
like you know you blink and it's gone
or again
by choosing to repeatedly attend
intend engage with things that you know
eventually lead to unwholesome
so they might not be bad
at its face value right there obviously
bad but you know like yeah but this will
lead to what he led so many times before
and you ignore that hint you ignore that
sign like you
I'm not guarding the sun stores yeah and
then when it comes to Breaking the
sensory strength it's like the most
natural decision at the time because the
mind is already inclined in that
direction way before
so now you can't stop that momentum
whereas if one practices sense restraint
then the possibility of seeing
um you know this context of of the
already Arisen nature of experience
proceeding yeah myself yeah
um that is possible that well yeah that
remains yeah that remains unobstructed
yeah yeah exactly so it's always there
but yeah the possibility of seeing it
yes and that's see that's that's the thing
and that's see that's that's the thing
like while the views are still
emphasized a person might be making
loads of effort like tremendous amount
of effort to keep clarifying that keep
clarifying what's already there isn't
before me not mine
but not actually purifying the sense
restraint withdrawal and not acting out
of intentions so you're still your f is
wasted in a sense
because your emphasis in the the the the
end not the beginning of it of that
development the first Chariot yeah
so yeah sure bring back that oh I remind
myself of the context but then also
continue and ask yourself why did you
lose the context in the first place why
do you need to keep reminding yourself
why do you need to keep rehashing things
that you understood why are they still
liable to doubt why are you bothered by
it oh well because the taming that
precedes it has not been developed not
sufficiently developed
so of course it's not going to be
perfect it's not like you're suddenly
going to stop everything else and you do
one two three sure technically
theoretically possible so the mind will
still be jumping at the end in the
beginning the middle and so on but as
long as you now know what comes first is
first uh you will not get like too carried
uh you will not get like too carried
away say in in spinning you know the
doubt and trying to figure it out while
you know that well this is the result
this is the symptom of an underlying
problem of insufficient
enduring things on the right level
insufficient restraint
and when I say sufficient restraint does
not mean okay so now I will really
restrain myself I will lock myself in a
little box I won't move I will barely
breathe I will not do anything because
that's not sense restraint that's now
self-torture sense restraint is when you are moving
sense restraint is when you are moving
around freely
throughout your day
and then you have an intention that's
directed towards sense desire
a version
distraction on the level of the body
speech or mind and that's which you
don't act if that's what you do
so they say that you
you
know that that's what you're supposed to
do hmm
you know enough of that
since you know Indulgence is wrong it's
going to block my progress everything
so I'm restrained I keep precepts
and then the pressure comes to break
those precepts yeah or break restraint
and all the knowledge you have
doesn't work yeah it's too distant it
becomes it's very nice it's right it's
it's it's it's deep and meaningful
whatever but it's it's yeah it's too
too far away so now that uh
and you and you break your restraint to
whatever degree
and you okay oh yeah and you you suffer
on account of it
and then you try again yeah to build up
the restraint
build up the restraint and listen you
know hear the same discussion on sense
restraint again and again and then the
pressure pulls up and once again you
with all that knowledge you you break
that sense restraint yeah so so what
and that's to say that's that's a person
who's just alone
doing the practice themselves
I think that's
you can get stuck in a loop
by yourself yeah
yeah so you've got all the information
about the dangers of essential
Indulgence you're trying to keep Central
student yet
yeah so then the question you yourself
are breaking it yeah and then trying
again and breaking it so you just
insulate it but that's the thing the
point is
when it comes to that when when your
inspiration and things you know kind of
drifts away into distance and now
pressure to break sense restraint is
there and you act out of it well see the
point is that that pressure to break the
sensor strength does not just magically
appear out of nowhere
there's not there's not come overnight
you will just like one moment you were
you were really like full on established
in the right context everything is clear
in the next moment it's oh you're about
to act out now all of it is gone
suddenly 100 miles away no
no it means there have been things in
between that that person was careless about
that that person was careless about
that that person was negligent
uh distract himself with
so it was accumulating the kind of
creative training in the opposite yeah
so it was exactly yeah yeah of course
whatever mind frequently thinks and
Ponders that's what it will incline
towards as a suit this would say so you
might not be thinking core stuff but
there is stuff on the level of
distraction indolence Oblivion and so on
that you are repeatedly repeatedly
engaging even in solitude and so on and
then the pressure is building up and the
clarity is drifting away
so that's what I said before like it's
recognizing the little things
and that's you know the Buddha said it
himself like the skillful cook and so on
like before these these states of mind
come and pressure you where you kind of
know you're gonna lose sense restraint
to a degree you start learning and
foreseeing like the the little the
little telltales
in the slightest fault Yeah well yeah so
this is not a fault technically but
every single time in the past when I
went and was engaging with with things
of this nature
uh here and there
I did have Central arrest arise later on
unrelated to this directly but still
related to the to the acts around it so
and that's when you build it up so
um it's not a kind of
um that pressure that has been
accumulated and now it's making you act
that doesn't come out of nowhere that's
the point
because it might seem that way because
for the same reason as we said when we
started this because you're still
emphasizing the end
failing to understand that what you're
going through is still the result of
other actions that you've been ignoring
cannot be otherwise
because sometimes you can feel like but
look I'm doing everything right
and now there is this pressure here that
would be impossible that would be
impossible so in the city there's an
analogy which is like yeah perfect for
describing what you just said go ahead
um so it says it's like when the rain
Pours Down on a Mountaintop
and the water flows downhill to fill the
hollows the crevices and the creeks
as they become full they fill up the
pools the pools fill up the legs the
legs fill up the streams it accumulates
dreams
become full they fill up the ocean yeah
that's the fuel for the ocean and that's
how it is filled up in the same way
when the factor of associating with oh
so these are the factors we didn't come
to yet then
um yeah so the when the factor of
associating with bad people is fulfilled
it's uh it fulfills the factor of
listening to an untrue teaching when the
factor of listening to an untrue
teaching is fulfilled it fulfills the
factor of a lack of faith
um and then and that's exactly what I've
been describing see like it doesn't mean
untrue teaching some some ridiculously
like wrong views no means simply the
wrong instructions instructions not
clear enough not emphasizing the right
things so you will lack faith means
basically you will lack uh ability
to emphasize that which doesn't seem
natural to emphasize that it doesn't
seem the most important or pressing
thing to emphasize
you want to emphasize it you'll
emphasize what you think you should
emphasize when you start hearing the so
somebody you come across the teaching
that's actually rightly expounded and
tells you well you should stop
emphasizing your views
you should stop emphasizing the end
result of it and start for seeing how
these things occur not in terms of
psychologizing and just explain to
yourself how this happened
but the moments the although the day
when you are deciding to go against the
sense restraint or distraction
you start emphasizing that and as I said
you will have no immediate criteria that
that's the right way to do it because
you're pressured on the level of the
views your pressure to clarify the views
to resolve the views to to attain the
views but it's like yeah well you got to
put that second and actually emphasize
body speech and mind actions rooting
greater version delusion
and they say okay I've been emphasizing
it but what now but now where is my view
where is my view well you have to have
faith and keep emphasizing the right
order of things the right development
and then your own pressure aware of my
views and what's happening will subside thank you
thank you
it's like um I think it relates back to
what you were just saying about that
pressure um
um
you're trying to be uh sense restrained
and then pressure builds up and some
points you break the central change and
they're not done I broke it again
it's like it can kind of
think that oh like oh because I acted
out of it therefore this danger and
problems that I thought I was
understanding must not be clear enough I
must think about it more and that's yeah
completely like the wrong yeah you can
think about it more but you you need to
realize that
doesn't matter how much you kind of
manage to sort of build up that
inspirational kind of thinking it will
okay the way it's natural things come
and go
um so so you still have to then
recognize that you really need to start
emphasizing that the behavioral aspect
of it and things that you want to do and
see the pressure will build up
inevitably um
um
and then you realize okay I need to act
out but then you still have an option as to
but then you still have an option as to
what you act out towards like yeah it
doesn't need to be sensuality like I
need to act out it's just too much
pressure yes I was careless I still
don't know to what extent and how
okay well go for a walk yes technically
it's acting out but it's not acting out
on the level of fully distracting
yourself with sense desires or winding
yourself up with your will and so on
because those kind of neutral acting
outs or not design wholesome acting out
won't take won't make you drift too far
away which means then you can recompose
better that's all that that the simile
in that would have said like even if a
monk having gone to the forest he's not
making any effort he's just sleeping all
day and having Central thoughts all day
long and just not nevertheless he's in a
more suitable environment his mind will
eventually calm down and compose
consequently you have the monk in the
middle of the village who is not
sleeping who is very diligent who is not
having lustful thoughts but he is in the
unsuitable environment with constant
exposure to side sound smell taste
touches so his mind will lose composure
um I need to kind of clarify these
things more so that there will be no
pressure to act out oh yeah it's so like
the whole point is that you know you
have to start by not acting out in the
face of everything that's how I must but
I must there is this pressure but I
don't act out of the pressure yeah so
like regardless of it and that's how you
would actually build up further Clarity
and that would then make that pressure
diminish in future
yes it's going to the Village or the
city or as he's uh traveling around
yes it's these gradual
uh just
yeah gradual
erosions it's like a cover-up where's
yeah in the forest is kind of more of a
the opening yeah you know things a bit
more uh apparent and clear to you as the
person who's there alone
your mind basically Forest it's like a
pool that doesn't have anywhere else to
spill further
like going on the base of the simile he
read so in the forest you pull of
central thoughts can fill up and
pressures and so on but there is nothing
further external that can keep spilling
further and and can cause more
proliferation and more distraction and
more density
so it remains in the environment that
kind of is not suitable for that growth
if you remain in that environment even
if the mind is careless sleepy it's on
lazy Central it will come down because
the environment just has nowhere else to
spill yeah and it's easier to ignore
those little faults when there's lots
going on you know it's maybe
being alone or isolated to a certain
degree you are your thoughts are clearer
so you kind of
those things that you are thinking doing
are clear to you
yeah do something
do something
yeah now again now that can become also
I'll never see any person ever again
but you you have to recognize no it's
all on the basis of where my intentions
are and I'm finding this the environment
and I'm finding this the environment
that can support like uh keeping the
clarity you have to my own choices
these little choices that would then
result in building up these these bigger
pressures that then I would not be able
to help myself and then act out of
so it's like the clarity so it's the
clarity so
you're not clear what you're doing these
little things you're not clear about the
little things that you're doing where
they're leading to but if you were clear
well why are you not clear
for example you're choosing it some well
which means you are clear means you're
no but you're choosing to ignore what
you already know so that's the reason
for the lack of clarity that's my point
like oh I'm not clear because I just
don't know what to do you already know
deep down you know exactly what not to
do
especially like you know you read few
sutas have listened to some talks it's
more than enough
to to paint a clear picture of what
should be done and what shouldn't be
done so yes the lack of clarity builds
up but not because you simply don't know
what you're doing but because on that
smaller subtler scale you're actually
going against the clarity that you know
you already have so what you know you
shouldn't do you're doing it and you're
ignoring it and then that builds up and
then it comes to the point of but you
obviously know you shouldn't do means
nothing you still do it because you
built it up so far
the pools have filled up so now you
can't just magically unplug it there so
say someone's doing that
constantly that's the Habit hmm of of
restraining
and then gradually
clipping slippings concealing knowing
that you're doing something wrong but
yeah knowingly kind of
and that's the Habit yeah that's the
Habit that's the Habit so what's the
first step to break out of that habit
yeah what's what will third Span in that
in that kind of thing what would throw a
spanner in that kind of thing
because I know yeah it is it's clear to
me so it's clear that it's wrong
you feel ashamed afterwards
you know you shouldn't have done it then
you don't do it for a while but then the
the carelessness the distraction the the
builds up the lack of clarity and then
you do it again and then same cycle
and then same cycle and then same side
what's the first step to break that
cycle
what is the the growth in the discipline
of a noble one
organizing a mistake of an offense as an
offense or well recognizing is not
enough well this person recognized it
every time but then slips away and the
recognition drifts away
so what's the what's the ACT that's
that's that's the spanner in the works
revealing it exactly yeah bringing it
out to the light confessing it to somebody
to the light confessing it to somebody
else so you feel that shame
you feel that weight you feel that
disgust even but it's out you can't hide
it anymore
that that last layer of owl this is just
in here
it's gone now
and that's already the practice that's
already a way of addressing it
it's like any addiction most people who
are headaches
basically they have to first they have
to say it but it doesn't just help
saying it internally hmm yeah
and then us I know heroin is wrong and
now they give it up they always have to
ask or speak to others say it out loud
in a group keep repeating it to
themselves I'm an alcoholic my name
such and such
was it also it helps with like you know
you might um sort of
feel to some you might feel ashamed of
yourself when you do these things but if
you really say it to somebody else it's
like you know it it comes out of your hands
you know it it comes out of your hands
absolutely yeah and it really forces you
to the world forces but it helps to take
up responsibility for it as well because
now okay it's not only me who knows
about this other people do as well so
yeah so it's like one thing it's as
monastics we we have that
you know that's the
protocols you know you break the rule
you confess it but as a like a layperson
just keeping five precepts eight piece
by themselves outside
that can be a big obstacle I reckon you
know because who yeah yeah yourself well
yeah so but no somebody wants to who wants to
so but no somebody wants to who wants to
train their mind and knows right is
right and wrong is wrong and what they
shouldn't be doing and then
they keep losing the context going back
to it building up
then we said
you said you said publicly like
to group to monk to two monks to five
monks just because it's like yeah this
is who I am and that's not gonna feel
Pleasant and that can be more than enough
and that can be more than enough
to to bring it back into shape
that's like it's the growth
in the practice